Hey. Up.
Get up!
They don't see us.
No, Wolf. Don't.
Your shoe!
Keep your toes covered
or you'll lose them.
Don't worry, we'll find you
a new one before we leave.
Why did you hide it?
If you get to Kolo,
tell my wife Klara
I will come for them.
Tell them yourself. Tonight.
You ready
Yeah.
No, he'll see you.
The Russians aren't far,
they'll be here by spring.
The spring?
We'll not make it
to the end of the week.
No one's coming for us.
-You'll get us all killed.
-We're already dead.
Come on.
-Monik, don't. Please.
-Monik, now.
Now. Move.
- Herr Polizeimeister,
my shovel, my shovel!
The shovel.
Sorry. Forgive me.
Don't kill me. I want to work.
I want to. I want to work.
I'm sorry. Forgive me.
- Kaputt, huh?
- Please.
Kaputt.
You really want to work?
Uh-huh.
Then you dig
with your hands, okay?
Lenz!
Your lucky day. Huh?
Hm.
Hey. Stop!
You and you.
What you're waiting for? Dig!
Move!
Dig! Dig!
On the drive back. Tonight
You're mad.
Will use the knife to cut
through the side
of the transport truck
-You already tried that.
With a rock,
now we've got a blade.
And then what?
They've already rounded up
every Jew from here to Lodz.
Where exactly will we go?
Have you seen anyone
arrive from Grabow?
It's only a few kilometers away
across the river.
It could be done.
No, it can't.
There's still a ghetto there.
I know the rabbi, Schulman,
he's with the underground,
trust me, he can help us.
But what if Goldman is right?
-What?
-If we escape,
they'll kill everyone.
They'll kill everyone
if we don't.
It's too dangerous
Every morning when
they take us out,
half don't come back.
We don't know if
we'll survive the day.
I overheard the Poles,
they say the Russians
will be here by spring.
Forget the Russians.
We have nobody but ourselves.
Goldman says if we just
hold on a little longer...
A little longer? For what?
Was burying your parents,
your sisters not enough?
Forgive me, Solomon.
I only meant that...
We must stop being afraid
if we want to live.
Or if we just want to survive.
Stop! Hey.
No talking. Hmm?
Okay, Oskar.
Take your hats off!
Have you done sorting before?
No, Scharfuhrer.
-You.
-No, Scharfuhrer.
-Yes, Scharfuhrer.
-Department?
Clothes, Scharfuhrer.
If you steal anything,
You try to escape,
you so much
as talk to each other..
-Are you listening
to the Scharfuhrer, dog?
-Jawohl.
-What?
-Jawhol, Polizeimeister.
Everything must be kept
in order, in the right pile.
You pick up the belongings,
you take it inside for sorting.
-Very simple.
-Yes, Scharfuhrer.
No talking,
no eye contact.
No speaking, no eye contact.
Come, everyone. Everyone off.
It is all right.
You're safe now.
-Go over there.
-This way.
Come a little bit closer.
Yes, please
Stand there.
Come, come.
Am aware of the hardships
you Jews have endured
since the start of the war.
And in the ghettos,
the horrific living conditions,
the disease
the lack of food.
But I assure you
your suffering is finally over.
This is the Kulmhof
Transit Center.
Let me be the first to tell you
that you have all been chosen
for good honest work.
From here you will be
transported immediately
to a new state-of-the-art
factory in Leipzig
where you will be given
hot meals, a place to stay,
and fair wages like
that of the German workforce.
Now, as you may know,
there has been a scare
of typhus in the ghettos.
And we cannot allow
that to spread to the factory.
Therefore. before
the long journey,
you will need to shower,
and all your clothes
and luggage will be disinfected.
Gold, money, foreign currency,
and jewelry are to be
deposited against a receipt
Do not lose your receipt
Since you will be asked
to present it
upon arrival in Leipzig.
Now please, gather your things.
Do so quickly so you can step
into the warmth of the castle
where you can
undress and shower.
Do not forget to
properly mark your baggage
so it can be identified later.
Goldstien? Goldstien.
Make sure to hand over
all valuables
hidden in your garments.
The steam from
the disinfecting oven
will destroy everything.
It would be a shame
to let your valuables be ruined.
Your number.
We all know how
stressful this period can be.
We believe it would be helpful
if you would write letters
to your families
that you have arrived
to your destination
and you're safe and healthy.
This way
You two.
Solomon? Solomon Wiener?
It's me, Aaron. From Kolo.
You don't remember me?
I'm Moishe's father.
Yes, yes, I remember you.
Did you see Moishe?
He was in the transport
two weeks ago.
Did he arrive at Leipzig?
Will we be working
in the same factory?
Uh, Moishe...
Take this gentleman's belongings
inside for disinfection.
-Yes.
-Now.
-You wrote your letter?
-Yes.
-You can go inside.
-Thank you.
Go.
Stop.
Mama! Mama!
[muffled screaming continues[
Hide this. Hide it.
My pockets are torn. Hide it.
You're risking our lives
over a pencil?
If people knew what
this place is,
what the Germans are doing,
they will help us.
Now take it, please. Come on.
Move.
Get them out.
Stop.
What you're waiting for?
They're not gonna
bury themselves.
Use every centimeter.
Keep them tight.
Good.
Look in the mouth.
Hey, hey.
No, no, no.
The fat ones on bottom,
the skinny one's on top.
Klara. Klara.
Klara!
Gutta! Abos!
My baby, my baby. Klara.
Kill me. Kill me now, please.
Let me be with my family.
Let me be with my family
You have to leave them.
-No. No.
-Leave them.
Kill me. Please.
I beg you. Please kill me
Yeah...
Continue to work. Come on.
Come on!
Come on. Come on.
- Back to work.
- Come.
-We have to keep going.
-Keep going?
Hey. Get up.
For what?
Hey! Continue working. Come on.
Come.
Get up!
Back to work. Hey!
- This is your last warning.
- Please.
Continue working now! Get up!
Come on.
Back to work.
Work!
Work.
- Ready?
- Now?
As soon as we are on the truck.
-Ready?
-It'll never work.
You'll get shot.
We're walking.
Move!
Tomorrow morning,
They'll have fixed the truck.
Stop!
So what is here?
We caught him outside
the woods, Polizeimeister.
He came to us looking for food.
Thank you.
Move!
Move faster!
Open it!
Everyone stand in line.
Hats off!
You can eat now.
You have to eat.
And tomorrow
we have to make sure we board
the back of the truck together.
If we get separated,
Solomon, do you know
the way to Grabow?
No.
This is the castle.
Grave site.
We run east through the forest
until we hit the river.
Follow it downstream.
Then head north
through the farms past Dabie.
The water is freezing.
So fall in and you're finished.
But it moves quick.
So, if we can find
a raft or something,
it'll take us downriver
and we'll be in Grabow
in 30 minutes.
We just have
to keep away from the roads.
And whatever happens,
do not trust the Poles.
I'm sorry about
your family, Michael.
We will do right by them.
Very good.
Hats off!
Let us lighten the mood, yes?
Play something.
No, no, no, no, no,
play something happy.
Something uplifting,
something to dance to.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, super!
Dance, dance, dance,
dance, dance, dance, dance!
Dance!
Louder. Louder. Louder.
Take your hats off!
And shoot.
Solomon, if you get to Grabow...
Thank... Thank you.
Not a word until morning.
What now, Szlamek?
what are we going to do now?
We run.
Run? We have no
one left to run to.
Wolf was right.
No one's coming for us?
As long as we're
still breathing,
there is hope.
Hope? All of
our families are gone.
There are other families.
One day the Germans
came into our ghetto
saying they were
in need of workers.
Only the strong
will be chosen, they said.
Each man should bring a shovel
and enough bread for two days.
My family,
like everyone else in Izbica,
were convinced that
we were off to a labor camp.
Better than starving
in the ghetto.
The Nazis put us in the truck
and we even stopped
on the way there
at a petrol station
so that we
could stretch our legs.
My neighbor, Bronshtein,
he wandered off,
the Nazis,
they didn't even notice.
And when the truck kept going,
he came running back,
banged on the side so that,
God forbid,
he wouldn't be left behind.
We had no idea.
No idea.
But as soon as we arrived here,
they made...
they no more effort
to conceal what
was really going on.
They took away
our shovels, our food.
I was taken out the forest
with three others
to dig.
The rest we buried that day.
My family, my...
My parents, my four sisters...
Not long after.
We have...
We have to get the word out.
We...
We have to warn our people
what this place is,
what it really, really is.
Do you think that will
bring an end to all of this?
I don't know.
I don't know, but if we succeed,
the next Brohnstein will not
be so keen to run back.
But how? How do we escape?
Just like
Wolf and Monik planned.
With what?
We haven't got a blade.
We have this.
We cut through the side
of the truck
on the way out tomorrow.
We take the river.
We stay off the roads
and we don't stop running
until we reach Grebov.
Yes?
Yes.
Listen, everyone.
Michael and I are going to
leap off the next transport
tomorrow morning.
Who's with us?
You think you're the first
to try to escape, young Szlamek?
Remember Zerlin from Leczyca?
Isserman and Greenberg
from Kutno...
No, they ran from
the castle or the gravesite,
not from the transport trucks
in the middle of the forest.
-There will only be
five or six Germans on us.
-And two never ran together.
We'll use the trees
for protection, draw fire
in different directions.
Exactly.
Join us, Goldman.
The Russians are less than
400 kilometers away.
We don't know that.
We only have ourselves
to rely on, Goldman.
You can take your chances here.
Michael and I are leaving.
Even if you make it
through the forest,
the first Pole you meet
won't hesitate to bring you back
for five Zlotys.
Grebow is only
a few kilometers away.
-Yes.
-The ghetto has not
been liquidated yet.
And there's a rabbi there,
he can help us.
And if by some act of God,
you make it there in one piece,
who do you think will be
staring down the barrels
of a firing squad
once they realize you're gone?
Goldman's right.
We've survived this long.
You are all welcome to join us.
If we succeed
and they take it out on you...
please know that I am sorry.
We will pray for you.
We will pray for all
those who suffered here.
Wolf. Wolf.
He was from Kutno, yes?
Yes?
Lodz.
Wolf was from Lodge.
Monik from Kutno.
Thank you, Felix.
Who else?
Jacob Zerlin, from Leczyca.
Josef Herskowicz, from Kutno.
Josef Herskowicz...
Motle, uh...
Motle Symkie, also from Leczyca.
Gecel Stajer, from Turek.
Josef Herskowicz, from Kutno.
Who else?
Moshe Pocar. From Kutno.
Moshe had a son here with him.
Uh, Josef? No.
Fabel.
Fabel Pocka.
-Fabel...
-Also from Kutno.
Isia Maja. From Zhezhani.
Jonas Ley, from Zhezhin.
-Who else?
-Jabob Szlamowicz, from Lodz.
Aaron Nusbaum, from Sanok.
Noah Judkiewicz, from Kutno.
Moshe Henikov. From Kutno.
Jacob Jacobitkevic...
Gecel Stajer, from Turek.
Isaac Szama, from Brzeziny..
My wife.
Klara.
Gutta and Abos Podchlebnik,
ages 5 and 7,
from Kolo.
Who else? Who else?
The late transport
has finally arrived!
Everybody out!
Back to the forest.
At least we don't have
to walk you dogs back, huh?
Good luck!
Goldman. Goldman...
Goldman. Goldman!
Goldman!
Goldman.
Hey, sit down!
-Sit down!
-Pleas, Herr Polizeimeister.
-Sit down, I said!
-It's important.
You sit down or you'll be
the first in the ditch!
Sit down, I said!
Spare a cigarette?
Yeah?
You like it? It's good, yeah?
Good cigarette, huh?
Yeah. You like it,
you have it, it's yours.
Yes, come on now!
There's another one coming!
You smoke it too, my friend!
Yeah!
Yes, you take it, you share it!
Go, smoke it!
Smoke it, smoke the cigarette!
Smoke it! Smoke the cigarette!
Ah, smoke the cigarette, huh?
Stop the truck! Stop the truck!
Stop the truck!
We'll freeze.
Go.
Hold on!
Michael! Hold on!
Michaeal!
-Hurry!
-I'm coming.
Hold on!
- Hold on!
- Solomon!
Michael! Hold on!
I've got you!
All right.
We need to keep moving.
My leg.
I've been shot.
Where? Show me.
Right here, right here.
Ah!
It passed straight through.
Do you want to know something?
I... I think I broke my leg
jumping off the truck.
Come on.
I guess... we're going
to be late for roll call.
Come on.
Do you think they'll report it?
I'm sure they've notified
every police station
from here to Lodz.
Two witnesses escaped.
Lange will have Lenz's head.
I'd pay money to see that.
Put a milk bottle on him.
What do you think's
going to happen to the others?
Shh. Do not move.
Just stare right back at them.
Come on. Come on.
Come on.
Stay low.
We need to head for the barn.
They'll hand us in
if they catch us.
We'll freeze out here.
Come on. Come on. Stay low.
What now?
-The motorcycle...
-Can you ride one?
Yes.
Shh...
Wait. She's alone.
-Railway uniforms.
-My husband's.
They might keep you safe
but please hurry.
That's all I can do.
Now go, please.
Thank you.
God be with you.
Hey!
Let's turn around.
What do we do?
Stop!
-Polish?
-Yeah.
Okay, come. Come help us.
Push!
Come on! Go, go, go, go, yeah!
Hey! Wait a minute.
Come here.
Come here, come.
What happened to your leg?
Oh, just an accident.
A group of Wehrmacht
fired at us just past Dabie.
A stray bullet.
-A stray bullet?
-Yes.
I don't think they meant to.
Franz!
-My medic will take a look.
-Oh, no, really.
There's no need.
I insist.
So you are with the railway?
-What?
-Your uniforms.
Ah, yes. Yes. Uh...
We are just on our way to
repair on the other track.
-Klodawa?
-Yes.
Well, that's our direction.
We will give you a lift.
Oh, thank you.
Thank you, but I have to...
I have to take him home.
He can't work in this state.
Where does he live?
Siedlec, just past Grabow.
All right. So we will take him.
I would not want to hold off any
service to the Fuhrer's trains.
No, of course not. I...
I, uh, have to refill
the bike anyway, so...
But thank you for your help.
I really appreciate it.
Thank you for your help, sir.
Well, thank you for your help.
We need to avoid the guards.
It's not just
the Germans I'm worried about.
The Judenrate?
-Here.
-Did Wolf tell you
where the rabbi's house is?
No.
But someone here will know.
It's empty.
It's curfew.
That was your leg.
- Who is it?
- Please, please
let us in. Please.
We're looking for
Rabbi Schulman.
You're not from here.
Who are you?
No, no. We're Jews. We're Jews.
We are escaped from
the Nazi camp at Chelmno.
We're looking for
Rabbi Schulman.
Abramson.
You know you can't break curfew.
Abramson?
Yes, yes, I know.
I have a problem with the lock.
Well, fix it.
Don't let the Germans
see it open during curfew.
You say you come from Chelmno?
-Yes.
-My son...
with his family,
they were sent off
to work in Chelmno.
Jacob Abramson.
He sent me
a letter from Leipzig.
Maybe you saw him.
No, I'm afraid not.
Please, sir, the Rabbi's house?
Go around back.
Take the side
street all the way down.
It's the second
house on the right.
The blue door.
Thank you.
Are you sure
you did not see my son?
Sorry, sir.
Rabbi Schulman?
-My--
-Shh. Quickly.
Please, please.
My dear Esther, bring
a bowl of water and some food.
Motle, go and fetch the doctor.
Hurry, but make sure
no one sees you.
Please, come sit.
Thank you. Thank you, Rabbi.
Solomon Wiener, from Izbica.
This is Michael Podchlebnik,
from Kolo.
We are escaped prisoners
from the Nazi camp in Chelmno.
Please, eat.
Amen.
Thank you, Rabbi.
There's a work camp in Chelmno?
It's not a work camp.
It's a death camp.
What are...
We have to be...
we have to be brief.
We passed a whole contingent
of Wehrmacht on our way here.
It won't take them long
to figure out who we are,
where we were headed.
What have you done?
I...
I know this will sound crazy,
and it is crazy,
we've just come from a place,
a true Gehenna on Earth.
What... What place?
The Germans are
building death camps,
factories designed to
exterminate our people.
We have buried an entire
Jewish community,
thousands,
with our own hands,
our own families.
-Rabbi.
-Thank you for coming.
Come, please.
Here. Sit, sit.
Thousands, you say? How?
With gas from a truck engine,
and then we buried them
in ditches in the forest.
Impossible.
This is the 20th century.
No one can annihilate
an entire nation
and get away with it.
Even during wartime,
it's unheard of.
And yet it is happening, Rabbi.
No more than
a few kilometers from here.
They tell them stories
of work in Leipzig,
and then they murder them.
Listen, we don't have much time.
We need your help.
We need to get a message out
and notify everyone.
No, I have a community here.
I cannot, I must
take care of them.
I cannot spread rumors.
Rumors?
Rabbi, these are not rumors.
Our people, they must be warned.-
-The world,
it must know the truth.
-It cannot be the truth.
I know the Germans here
they would not do this. No.
-Rabbi.
-No, no, there is
a war going on.
People are sick, scared,
frightened for their lives.
This will cause panic.
You will scare them even more.
But they should,
they should be scared. Look.
Look at these names.
No. These are just the ones
that we remember.
Look at my hands.
Every day they bury a thousand
of our brothers and sisters.
Look at me and tell me
you don't believe me, Rabbi.
Look at me!
I...
Oh, no!
Nothing I can say
will do it justice.
You have to see
it with your own eyes.
It will be the last thing
you ever see, Rabbi.
We came here so that you,
your family, this community
will never have to.
Why, why, why, why are you here?
I'm just a rabbi.
We were told that you had
connections to
the underground in Warsaw.
Oh! No, no.
Who, who told you this?
Wolf Kaminski.
Rabbi, can you help us?
Are you expecting anyone else?
No.
Rumkowski.
We heard
you may have some guests.
Guests?
No one came looking for you?
Who would come during curfew?
Then you
don't mind if we come in?
I was just about to daven.
Please, join me.
Your father would
be happy to know
that you didn't miss prayer.
That should hold
the Judenrate off for a while,
but they'll be back.
Tell me what happens in Chelmno?
We, we, we will
write everything down.
But we need to know
that you can get this out.
Have, have
you something to write on?
Tell me everything.
The camp started operating
on the 8th of December, 1941,
when the first transport
of Jews arrived from Kolo,
Michael's village.
Over 700 were gassed that day.
They, they were,
they were the first.
the first,
the first day I arrived,
my...
My...
My, my...
We will get everything done.
This will reach the underground
and they will get it to London.
I promise you this.
People will not remain silent.
The world will tremble.
Thank you.
I am aware
of the hardships
you Jews have endured
since the start of the war
and in the ghettos.
The horrific living conditions,
the disease, the lack of food.
But I assure you,
your suffering is finally over.
This is the BBC
reporting from London.
We will now present
a special broadcast
about horrible atrocities
committed on the Jews
by the Hitlerite occupant.
Here in London, we have received
detailed information describing
the entirety of the cold,
calculated system,
in which thousands of members
of the Jewish community
are being shot, gassed,
and cruelly murdered.
These inhuman crimes
committed on innocent people
cry vengeance to heaven.
They cry for a fair
and strict punishment...